All right. Hello, welcome everyone.
It is June 27th, 2025 and this is the
second quarterly round table of the year
of 2025. So here we go.
Welcome to active inference institute.
We're a participatory online institute
that is communicating, learning, and
practicing applied active inference.
This is a recorded and an archive
liveream. So provide any feedback so we
can pro improve our work. All
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we'll follow video etiquette for
live streams and see if anyone joins
along the way.
Here's a slide you can screenshot if you
want to have some short links that will
stay good forever even though their
reference may change. and ways to get
involved.
Here's what's on the agenda today.
First, we will go over some institute
scale updates. Then talk about some
project scale updates. Look a little bit
towards the second half of the year.
Then have uh a view from the desk of why
active inference and why the institute.
And then I will look at the live chat to
see if there are any comments or
questions that can be addressed.
So here we go. Starting with some
updates at the institute scale. If you
go to 2025.active.institute,
you will find a living entry point for
the year as it happens. And
ecosystem.active.institute
is the entry point. So one piece that'll
be fun and new today is there will be
this red shaded box with specific
requests or opportunities. So if you're
looking for ways to contribute, ways to
get involved, these are just specific
ways that you can pick up on some slide
that you find interesting and take it
from there. So if that's interesting,
jump on in to the ecosystem document and
learn a lot more. Okay. Today we have a
special announcement which is that the
institute has been awarded a $270,000
grant from the survival and flourishing
fund to support work on the AI
capabilities and alignment consensus
project
AICP.
AI CICP is a multi-year initiative
designed to reshape the conversation
around AI capabilities alignment and
regulation by combining high impact
journal collections, in-person
discussionoriented workshops and
academic media content for public
outreach. The project aims to bridge the
divide between AI doomers and
accelerationists through deeply
exploring the meaning of world models
and agency and what these concepts mean
for AI development.
Adam Saffron at the Allen Discovery
Center at TUS University is the creator,
principal investigator, and organizing
editor for this project. The grant
supports also an expanded team to assist
with efforts to manage the special
issues and workshops, including these
contributors. Lead Assistant Editor
Victoria Clamage, media lead and
workshop organizer Michael Garfield,
workshop project supervisor Amelia
Donley, and workshop experience designer
Caitlyn Lynch. Email Adam if you have
any thoughts or questions. And moving
from that project scale announcement to
what it means for the institute today.
We are happy to announce that grant and
there are many more grants to come. So
consider proposing or funding a grant
with or for us. There's going to be a
lot of ways that this single grant helps
us develop the administrative ability
to, for example, receive and disperse
grants. The oversight that we need and
look to have and the wisdom in choosing
different kinds of ways to allocate our
resources, financial, attentional,
otherwise.
And with taking a small to zero overhead
on different grants and different
philanthropic pathways, I hope that
people can see some exciting
possibilities for ways that we can host
all kinds of work. So looking forward to
the AI CACP project and what they all
get done over the coming year and also
ways that we can turn that N equals 1
today into an N equals question mark
exclamation point and plus tomorrow with
all that can happen when we work
together this way. So thank you also to
the team to to Adam Saffron and
colleagues and of course to the the
funders. This is an exciting
opportunity.
It brings the first taste of funded
project scale work not yet funded
administrative work but some project
level work that is again really critical
and appreciated for building our
capacities.
Okay, moving on.
In the second quarter of 2025, we
continued to receive excellent
engagement from our scientific advisory
board, which is our informal research
and education guidance group. Many of
them joined meetings. A lot of them also
engaged in different ways at the project
scale, showing up in Discord, showing up
in the documents,
uh, mentoring.
And if you want to learn more or engage
on this topic, check out the cool work
that they are all doing as individuals
and consider applying for the SAB for
2026.
If this sounds like something that you
might like to be engaged in, providing
strategic guidance informally,
mentorship, all these different ways
that SAB members can be our advocates,
some of whom I see in the chat even now
about our formal organizational and
strategic aspects. It has been great to
work with Dr. Vice President and
Secretary Alexandra
and we've had good times thinking a lot
about how to improve the administration
of what we do at the institute scale.
This quarter we also engaged with Dana
which is a professionalization group for
Delaware registered nonprofits of which
we are and working with Earl from Dana.
We had a training with a board of
directors joining. That was a great
milestone in the improvement process for
our board of directors. It spurred many
important conversations and gave us a
lot of ideas about how we can improve
and professionalize the board of
directors. So, thank you to the BOD and
to Alexandra for the institute scale
work that they do. And it isn't too
early to think about being an officer or
a BOD member in a future year. So look
into everything more if that sounds
exciting to you.
All right. Research fellows. We
currently have five research fellows.
They are individuals affiliated with the
institute. We do what we can to support
and accelerate their research. If you
want to learn a bit more about their
research specifically, you can go to
this link on the page and I will share
updates from JF and John later in this
round table that they presented. If
you're looking for other ways to get
involved with this research fellows
program, first you could donate to make
targeted donations to their projects.
Those are funds that can only be spent
for a donor advised purpose. consider
applying to be a research fellow. We're
also going to think about what other
types of fellows make sense to add in
the future like education and so on. And
if you're just interested in this
program in any other way, get in touch.
Partnerships. We did not add any new
partnerships this quarter. However, we
advanced some discussions meaningfully
with other partners that we will
announce when the time is right.
Partnerships are structured
relationships between the institute and
other organizations who are looking to
make meaningful visible custom impactful
contributions to active inference in the
open source ecosystem. It really means
and helps a lot in terms of our
sustainability and reach. And there are
a variety of ways that value is created
and added on both sides of that
partnership. So, if you're interested in
being an advocate for your organization
and exploring what it might mean to
create some type of partnership, check
out the link at the top of the page or
get in touch otherwise.
Just about philanthropy and support
overall, we're in our fifth year of
operations and as always, but
especially, we're at a critical juncture
in terms of how we proceed. What do we
really do at the institute scale? What
do we offer? We're a 501c3 taxexempt
nonprofit and providing financial and
inind support really is making
differences for what we do. So the
donate.activeinference.institute
link will always be good and the request
is provide a donation if as when how the
time is right. absolutely no worries
otherwise. Uh personal and
organizational commitment is that
activities and materials remain
available without financial barrier. So
what's priceless is that which doesn't
have price which is to engage and
support the institute through your
engagement and and many other ways.
Okay. On to the project scale.
We continued several educational
institute hosted projects the active
inference ontology the audiovisisual
production the textbook group and the
journal. So just to give a few
highlights from these
the textbook group during this past
quarter we
finished up with cohort 7
got to the halfway point in cohort 8 and
when we pick back up in probably August
with the textbook group we will resume
with chapter 8 we will pick up with
chapter 9. I'd like to give a special
appreciation to Andrew Pasha who
facilitated half of the meetings for the
last phase of activity with cohort 7 and
8. Andrew brings a lot of hands-on
expertise in the modeling and also an
increasingly deep knowledge of the
textbook and related topics and and a
variety of fields. So, it was epic to
sit back and watch that facilitation
unfold. And thank you again, Andrew. If
you're interested in the textbook group,
there's a few ways to get involved.
First, you could participate in this
coming phase of activities. If you've
been looking at that golden ring and
sort of lavenderesque cover from 2022
and wondering if there was a way to have
community and have engagement around
reading that book and working through
it, this is a good opportunity. Also,
you could volunteer further to
facilitate or scribe at live meetings or
do a variety of asynchronous
contributions like adding and updating
questions, developing examples,
computationally,
mathematical, unpacking background
materials, so many different ways that
we can work asynchronously to make these
materials more available and useful. And
now three years on from this textbook
group's continuation, it's also
possibility to propose facilitating
another book. That could be Nave's
recent book. It could be Sanjiv Nam
Jooshi's upcoming book. It could be some
other book. But we have the format, we
have a template, we have the
communication channel. So, as with so
many activities, it just takes one
person to raise their hand say at this
time once a week or once a month I could
do this or I could see who would come to
that strange attractor. So, if that's
you and you want to facilitate a
textbook group, then let's uh explore
that.
All right. In terms of
audiovisisual production, we continue to
produce open-source audiovisisual
materials and release them into the
active inference ecosystem where they
take on lives of their own speaking to
different people, training AI, all those
kinds of things. There were 36 streams
in the past quarter and now we are up to
624 overall, which does include the
textbook groups. However, several
hundred of other kinds of streams as
well.
Let's look at which streams happened
this quarter.
See if anybody has any favorites.
video.active inference.institute
is the table for all the videos.
Okay. Guest streams we had 101 up to
113.
uh variety of topics. Just giving a
single word for each one of these
topics. There was autonomous vehicle
navigation,
scientific explanation and agency,
computers and consciousness,
cognitive transitions, collective
predictive coding, systemic deviation,
foundation agents, affective states,
semantic information communications,
free energy, attentional naring,
narrowing, and cognitive rigidity. the
triple equivalence
amongst neural networks, basian graphs
and touring machines,
dynamic systems out of thermodynamic
equilibrium, brain-like variational
inference, and the basian mechanics of
economic choice. So, the guest streams
are sort of the grab bag with many
different uh topics. Some are right down
the middle with the act of inference,
others are a little bit adjacent, but
very relevant. So, a lot that could be
said, some of which was said during
those streams, other things could be
said in the comment section or or
otherwise. Um, great guest streams.
And then there were also
looks like I pasted in the same
screenshot twice, but there was other
streams too that you could find at
videos link.
If any of these topics like video or
multimedia production, trans media
production, education, communication,
awareness, all these different topics,
it would be awesome to have some people
get involved in the project. There's a
variety of ways that one can contribute
behind or in front of a microphone or a
keyboard. uh ways that someone can help
contribute to the well-developed
pipeline we have for inviting guests and
carrying out streams as we do or like
Shannon Dobson or Darius PW did to step
up and propose a new series. So
different ways at at at different levels
but it doesn't require expertise in
these topics. It's almost quite
literally the opposite of that with so
many of these projects that the person
who is curious and motivated jumps in.
The person with expertise or not, who
isn't doesn't
into the research section.
There were several institute hosted
research projects. RX infer learning and
development group, knowledge
engineering, active blocker and active
inference.
So in the RX Infur group, we continued
to support open- source development and
documentation around the RX Infur
ecosystem with this quarter several
packages sprouting off within that
ecosystem, a server API and all these
other different pieces of the puzzle
that they're working on uh at Reactive
Base, the GitHub username where the core
RX infur methods are hosted and also at
lazy dynamics and also personal GitHub
repos and other open- source blogs like
Kobas's blog. We are as always
developing our KOD documents to have all
kinds of information, rabbit holes,
links in and out and we continued weekly
meetings up on through the end of this
month.
If you are curious about ways to
implement statistical models that are
basian, active inference and otherwise,
uh, check out rx infer.jl.
There's a variety of open- source repos
and examples, and the team and the
community want to see where people hit
blocks and frictions. So see if you can
clone the repo or even if you don't get
that far, what stopped or prevented you
along that step and let's work to make
these packages more available and useful
because software is non-trivial. RX
infer is a
big
package, let's say. It does a lot of
things. It has a lot of possibilities
and so that can make it a little bit
hard to get into and that's something
that has improved over the almost 2
years that we've been working with the
package.
Check out the engineering channel in
Discord where a lot of the RX Infur devs
and people using the package are
chatting. So you can ask questions in
there. And if you want to facilitate
some of these open meetings around RX
infer very specifically or a related
project like more about software or
systems engineering. As with other
projects, just email in to propose a
time. You may be that 0 to one person
who offers that ability for others to
rally around that time and it just gives
visibility to even the learning. So you
don't need to know every aspect to wait
to get started. Just jump in wherever
you're at. Work on it privately. Work on
it openly.
All right. We are in planning for the
fifth applied active inference
symposium. So some people may remember
in November 2024 we had a
very
fun symposium. We had about 30
presenters and they gave a variety of uh
inputs into different aspects of how
they were applying active inference that
year. And we are looking right now
towards a November 12th to 14th
uh date for the 2025 symposium. So still
about four or five months away.
At this point, we are seeking presenters
who would like to present their work or
lead an interactive workshop as well as
sponsoring organizations who would like
to support this work or get involved at
the symposium in some way. So, check out
the symposium short link and I hope that
you will find something useful here.
It's been
cool year after year to see as the field
and the ecosystem grow, what does it
mean to apply active inference continues
to develop and take on some new
uh features, let's say. And the focus
for this
uh symposium, we're still writing a lot
of the the positioning and it will
partially depend on which presenters and
sponsoring organizations get involved,
but we're going to focus a lot on
industry and different ways that active
inference is being applied.
All right, into the ecosystem projects.
So there are two forms that we point to
again and again and again and again
which are the prepare and the measure
forms. And if you want to learn more
about the first principles grounding of
prepare and measure, check out Chris
Fields's 2023 course on the physics's
information processing. But big picture,
these are like two inboxes,
stable links that will always be good
where you can say what you're preparing
to do. It's like preparing to go out
into the field. Where are you heading
out? And that could be a project that
you just want to let us know that you're
going to head out upon or maybe you
could ask for some kind of visibility or
support like having the project listed
at the projects page or having some
other request like is this something
you're going to go out on either way or
is this something that if you had
funding you would do or if you had a
collaborator you would do. So whether
it's a all systems go or a conditional
proposal that's what the prepare form is
for. And then there's measure, which is
like you're back. Now what? So what did
you measure? Did you see a bird? Did you
write software? Did you publish a paper?
Did you do a podcast? Is there a blog?
Did you learn something? These are all
different kinds of measurements that you
can make. And that's that two-stroke
engine of preparing to make a
measurement, setting up your quantum
reference frame, and then making that
measurement, the sense making on the
inbound. And then those measurements
form what we put into the quarterly
roundts and also the monthly
newsletters. So we exhort people towards
the end of the month. But of course the
measure link is open 24/7
and we really look to continue to
develop these streamlined gradients of
reporting and information flows in the
ecosystem
to ground those flows in active
inference and the free energy principle
cognitive systems concepts and think
about how do we design and make that
modular and effective. So let's jump
into some of these updates.
Okay. So, the theoretical neurobiology
group, TNB group, is a long-standing
research meeting group that Professor
Carl Fristen hosted at UCL. And the TNB
has now been hosted at the institute for
several months. We work with the chairs
of the TNB to support their work and
make the participation more available
and the proceedings more accessible.
If you're interested in the TNB, first
off, this short link is awesome and
gives information on how you can get
involved in the live meetings, but also
whether you join those live meetings or
not, there will be some efforts in the
coming quarter to add and check metadata
on public recordings in order to
integrate the TNB videos that are
publicly available with the broader
videos database so that we can do the
transcription and indexing and the
retrieval augmented generation and all
the different kinds of conversations,
all these different things that we do
for the journal and bringing the TNB
into that fold. So this is an example of
like if you're just learning or you're
an intern or you're just wanting to see
a little bit broadly what is happening
then this is a way to integrate your
epistemic drive with a huge contribution
which would be to go through these
videos watch the ones you like but just
check do we have the date the person the
title all these kinds of things curate
that metadata
These are things where it seems like
someone else is going to do it and yet
it just takes one person to step up and
do it. We know that it can be done. It's
a way where if someone wants a task to
do that has permanent impact.
Great way to enter.
Okay.
Here and the images that are on the side
were were generated through Perplexity
based upon the text of the person's
update. So research fellow JF Clair
reports in the symbolic cognitive
robotics project. He updated his
published paper on the implementation of
the app perception engine. He split his
sprawling agency repo into separate
prologue repos for implementation of the
app perception engine, the actor
framework and the utilities and the
agency itself.
Currently he is coding the ground level
of society of mind which is the
collective intelligence system
with sensor andector cognition actors CA
coding brings clarity which is a very JF
statement to make. He writes I think I
have a good handle on life cycles of
sensor andector cognitive actors and how
they interact within the CA's one layer
up in the agent society of mind. I'm
also iterating on the actor framework
whenever I find it to be lacking. A
detailed function design of artificial
agency was completed. Implementation is
underway and the project is advised by
SAB members Elliot Hower and Avala Gwen
Kalu.
Okay.
from the active inference account of
belief updating in PTSD project. Andrew
Pasha, Jeremy Cooper, Helen Sun and
Angelos Kryptos report. We repaire we
prepared based upon our current draft
work and preliminary model results
extended abstract and then anonymously
submitted it to the sixth international
workshop on active inference IY 2025.
Ian Tennet, who's been on several live
streams and is on the SAB, reports,
"Following the fourth applied active
inference symposium, I discovered that
one of the presenters, Leonardo Müller,
works here at ARU at the Cambridge
Institute for Music Therapy Research. We
discussed our shared interest in active
inference and collaborated to record
interviews for each other's YouTube
channels. Uh inner sense for Ian's and
music-minded for Leonardo's. They are
now discussing a paper on archetypes. We
have met two milestones so far recording
the interviews and have unmet milestones
for writing a paper.
Okay. Some updates from interns Satyaki
Maitra and Harshel Shaw report.
Over the course of the project, we have
slowly crafted an improved an
implementation of an active inference
model deployed in a Microsoft Airsim
drone with a goal of eventual realorld
implementation. With a newly implemented
sensor fusion and final improvements to
the model, we have the tools necessary
to begin moving to a real drone and
we'll begin this new phase of the
project. Here's a brief summary of the
project. We developed a hierarchical
active inference framework in AirSim
that uses LAR and/or depth camera data
to infer latent suitability maps for
navigation. The drone minimizes expected
free energy to select feasible adaptive
trajectories in complex environments,
achieving high simulation success rates
in GNSS denied scenarios, GPS denied
scenarios.
Michelle Venucci intern reports with
Peter Blum as thesis supervisor.
After an initial thesis proposal which
focused on studying active inference in
an agent whose internal states and
dynamics are defined by a cellular
automaton, we pivoted the research to a
more theoretical discussion on intrinsic
motivation as surprise minimization or
knowledge seeking within the AIXI model
setting. Updated versions of the thesis
draft can be found at this website.
This is a report that I made. There have
been major updates to the open-source
generalized notation notation GNN
repository.
Some of these updates were covered in
active infant stream 14.2,
GNN for generative model supply chains,
a golden spike moment for multi-agent
trajectory planning with RX infer.jl
and inferent stream 14.3. The sound of
uncertainty, auditory rendering of
generative models in the field of
streams.
Research fellow John Boy reports from
the Cognar ecosystem facilitating group
cognition at scale project. There have
been group meetings and development with
John, Tim L. Jesse, Jeff S. Lee E,
Michael L. Updates include reading
project materials, participating in
group discussions, co-drafting,
follow-on plans and analysis,
dissemination of project materials,
group discussion, development and
implementation planning, drafting and
sharing of project technology
development and implementation plans in
PDF form to inform and invite others
regarding contribution and opportunities
for cognar project implication
uh impact application.
Refine scope and operational definition
of stick figure implementation
prototype.
All right, next project measurement. In
the project, the Einstein model of a
solid as a model of the mental apparatus
from the economic perspective of
psychoanalytic theory, Theodoris Alferis
along with Dr. Tisano Kibazi, a
associate professor, clinical professor
of psychiatry at Columbia University and
professor Constantinos
Akin Bulis and TUA report. They are
engaged in continuous collaboration and
exchange of ideas for manuscripts to be
published to reputable journals.
Intern Allegra Grunberg reports uh
this research presents a novel
theoretical framework for transforming
the employment ecosystem through the
integration of the free energy principle
collective intelligence methodologies
and the adaptive socioeconomic system
ads framework operationalized via the
sensemaker tool. The study addresses
critical misalignments between education
provision, labor market demands,
graduate preparedness, and recruitment
processes within the UK employment
ecosystem utilizing UCL STE
as a paradigmatic case study. The
proposed framework employs FEP based
modeling to minimize stakeholder
uncertainty, optimize goal alignment,
and enhance job matching and skill
development processes through systematic
collection and analysis of micro
narratives from 100 participants
comprising students, alumni, faculty,
and employers. The research establishes
a continuous feedback mechanism that
identifies emergent properties within
the employment system. This approach
enables both reactive adaptation to
current economic conditions and
proactive anticipation of future labor
market demand.
All right,
I'm going to pause there
to read the existing comments just to
get here. So, I'll put a horizontal line
in the live chat. I'll read all the
comments above there and then we'll
carry on with the next section.
Math for Wisdom says, "Great and
congratulations." Thank you, Andreas.
Haptivist, bravo. Thank you, Haptivist
aka Michael. Gia Maximalist 4647.
Thank you for the emoji. Ashot writes,
"How to find the nave 2025 book." Thank
you, Andreas. The book is called A Drive
to Survive. It's at MIT Press.
Ashot writes, "Do we still have early
access to Sanjie Nam Josie's upcoming
book?" As far as I know, the book is in
its uh final editing stages, the first
of the two books. So, I don't think that
there's further access provided to the
earlier draft. But as soon as we can
start arranging the textbook group and
the availability of the book in its
published form, you can expect that we
will eagerly work with it.
Upcycle Club provides a super chat.
Congratulations to all. Thank you up
club for all the support.
And Sachaki says, "Thanks for the
spotlight." Thank you, Sachi. All right,
a few speculative directions now for the
second half of 2025.
So, what was before is now. So, how to
what if?
These are directions that are known
unknowns. We could say of course the
unknowns unknowns always take us by
surprise and delight but these are
directions that are conditional upon
people's interest their resourcing needs
emergence that is yet to happen
different volunteer contributions and
resourcing funding or grants that might
come in everyone's intentional regime
developments in the ecosystem all these
kinds of things that could happen and
change. So, as these are presented, and
there's just a few of them,
what would be of epistemic and pragmatic
value for you? What else should we
consider and co-explore? And that could
be something like that you want to put
into the suggestion box, so to speak, or
maybe you are that co-explorer.
So, first in the DI decentralized
science and publishing area,
we have a page that currently is just a
stub on the DI nodes platform.
If you would like to help as a editor or
platform use designer here kind of blaze
a trail into the DI publishing, there
could be amazing opportunities to use
this platform andor other DI and nano
publishing affordances to support
durable accessible modern publishing
credentiing cryptographic attestation DI
integrations peer review valuing peer
review all these kinds of topics that
we've been talking about in DI for years
and ways to make it applicable. This is
one way that people can look into those
topics.
And in knowledge engineering, so from
2022 with Blue and RJ, we did a
systematic meta analysis of the
literature. There's an interactive front
end. There's open source code and we
look to develop that knowledge
engineering resource with some volunteer
effort and with some partnerships and
further resourcing. There's a lot of
ways that we could develop this. We
could curate resources better across
different documents. People have sort of
semi-independently prepared different
reading lists. We have Zotterero. We
have all these different sources of
bibliographic information and this could
be integrated.
Sanjieve as part of the process of
writing his textbook has also made a
open-source repo aifb
which scrapes literature databases and
so I've played with this a little bit we
could develop on what Sanjieve has put
out there as his milestone and work to
better pull from databases for keywords
filters all those kinds of things and
basically advance the state of the
biblioraphic services that we provide to
the ecosystem. So that finding good
applicable research, finding papers with
code, being able to use the ontology to
search and filter all these kinds of
things that we could offer would be
great and and provide services to
research and to partners and all around.
Okay, those are the only two speculative
directions. The next section will be the
view from the president's desk. So I
guess I'm like here kind of looking out
looking out as the world the physics of
the world sort of melt and perspectives
fuse. These are just some loose thoughts
from the drawers. And there's a lot more
where this comes from. So, wherever
people find this relevant, these are
just like a few little snippets from
what happens in the officer and board of
directors room
could be
interesting. I just thought why not give
a little exposure to some of these
things that I'm writing anyway and await
people's live chats but give a few kind
of just personal not even necessarily
organizational or fully formed thoughts
but
go through a few of these
and and to call back to the agenda the
the the the motivator was
why active inference I I mean why not
just say we're doing statistics on
computers or why have an institute why
why why is it not enough just to say
well people should really like you know
look at this method
okay
open science means that the active
inference institute disseminates
products and provides services
intentionally respectfully and
professionally with a focus on the
accessibility rigor and applicability of
active inference we seek to raise up and
activate the available, the rigorous,
and the applicable.
Please enjoy nested scales of agency,
the ecosystem, the subset of the
ecosystem that we curate, and of course
all that's out there far far beyond what
even we know we don't know. The
population, our peer and partner
organizations,
the colony scale, the organizational
scale, that's our organizational active
and static elements,
the task group, the projects, the
products, the services that are offered
and the people, the the humans out
there, the nestmates, the AI agents, all
of that. So in this nested systems
conceptualization,
we're just one thread through it
to join in to be part of the underground
slash inside
to be part of the production act infer.
What does that really mean? Well, I can
give one take here, but it's up to each
in their own way.
First act. Start and lead with action.
Do interact.
It could be privately. It could be in an
online space. It could be with
anformational artifact. It could be with
an active element. Start wherever.
Infer, update, and go from there. Change
your mind andor change the world how you
know it and how you don't. And with that
two-stroke engine serve on slashin
slashwith your own alignment trajectory
across internal blanket and external
states in that interplay of act and
infer quote this is not a third step and
that's sort of them agree crossover.
So why active inference and why the
institute
attending the case
everything/distribution
has a precision estimation whether it is
modeled or not the buck stops somewhere
and precision stops somewhere in the
trivial simple or toological case which
is ultimately essentially omnipresent
which is to say things ultimately
trivially no matter how partially known
are how they are. It is a drock delta a
point mass distribution.
Distributions could change with respect
to time dynamic or updating or not. It
could be static or fixed.
So even even things that change how they
change how they change how they change
with respect to that are fixed. The
implication it ultimately is as it is
which includes how it changes and how it
is known and interacted with by any
agent. So in specific cases and of
course this is the cerebrum pun cases
can be both specific situations like
case management or it could be
categorical linguistic semantics.
In specific cases there can be any kind
of distribution like awareness of
awareness of awareness of itself and
other compositional scenarios. More
information on that is to be found in
the cerebrum paper and reba.
Even outside of considering this nested
case as metacognitive or even further
for those who dabble into the
phenomenological
instrumentally kofkov we can think of
this a arrow b relational kernel in
terms of basian hyperparameters priors
over priors there's always an arrow
pointing to something or in a more
generic causal basian graph setting
blanket states so what does this case
sensitivity bring what what Does
organizing around it have to do with
anything?
With this modeling commitment to the
particular partition of the free energy
principle and the predelection for
precision in generative modeling,
there's a tremendous expressiveness
and openness to describe cognitive
ecosystems. Sometimes summarized as the
framework says less so that we can say
more, do more. The specific generative
model, the the particular case as it
were, is an instance of a more general
category of models, which is to say that
all that is the case is a subset of all
that could have been the case.
All that could have been the case
includes what actually was the case.
Active inference modeling, at least in
our case-sensitive synthetic
intelligence posture, gives analytical
coherence across cognitive phenomena,
also known as the whole iguana or the
neat side of the equation. Specifically
in terms of unified notation for
arbitrary systems. So talking about
unification of cognitive phenomena
within the human system or the ant
system, attention, memory, anticipation,
all these different kinds of properties
of systems can be unified
in aspiration and in notation and
execution. Importantly,
these case-sensitive notational
representations and methods which take
account of both generalities as well as
the Blakeian man particulars. They are
not uncashable checks
with these two eyes open structured
representation both as parameterized
that's in particular and parameterizable
that's the all moves perspective
allows an operational semantics of
generative models. These are models that
do stuff, models that we do stuff with.
Examples of the kinds of stuff that can
be done with generative models are
incipiently described by the modules
associated with the generalized notation
notation. Execution as a simulation, use
as a descriptive statistical model,
transformation into category theory,
representation, type checking, resource
estimation, use it as input for
generative AI, service provisioning, use
in onlogical analysis, rendering in
different computational settings,
visualization of model structure,
outputs,
audio
representation, and more and more.
So
now thinking well
and to say we support the open education
and research on these topics.
Now a little bit about roads and
notation.
This is the figure 1.2 from the 2022
textbook which summarizes the low road
and the high road to active inference.
We want to have notation systems and
deployment methods for generative models
with expressive methods for and nested
addressable spaces of.
So these are going to be spaces starting
from the largest space on through
smaller spaces. Describe, design,
render, simulate, analyze, fit, assess
performance of models.
That's to say there's a larger set of
models that we can describe
than we can render. There's a larger set
that we can render than the ones that we
could actually simulate. There's a
larger set and so on. That's to say, we
can describe recipes we cannot cook and
that's a good thing. So, it's great that
we have the high road that we can
describe systems that we can't
necessarily take along every step of
this way. And some of the things on the
low road, they're already out there in
the world like biology. Other things out
there are remaining to be built. But
with this top-down view, we have the
ability to describe in a unified
framework. So performance is about
specific generative models. Performance
is like whether it's a category of
models or it's always situational. What
is the performance of this model with
this data set in this situation on that
assessment etc.
and performance on one benchmark like
the high jump let's say or a suite of
measures like the decathlon like are you
interested in the precision and the
recall and you're also looking at
resource use it's relational measurement
or assessment or characterization that
is just a view upon the primary
phenotype of that model
thinking about projects that are in and
around the ecosystem they have these
fitness and performance wants and needs.
Like thinking about some of the projects
mentioned earlier, it's like a
self-driving car that is safe in this
condition or a drone that is effective
under these circumstances or a model of
PTSD that is useful for this person in
this way. And all of that, all of those
useful little nuggets of parameterized
models as parameterized as structured as
built, that's all happening within this
larger space of the models that could
be. Like all it is is a subset of what
could be. And those generative models of
what could be include the baroque, the
absurd, the tiny, the useful, the cute,
funny, interesting, healthy, tasty,
generous, small, large, educational,
perplexing, all the above. So we have
free energy principle coming from the
high road. That's the particular
partition, path, lease action, all that.
and we have an increasing portfolio of
engineering methods on the low road and
we meet in the middle with active
inference. So now getting to the
institute
consider that we have pair-wise
information or distance measures in
terms of software 1.0. So we can take a
syntactic
way to look at differences between
strings. We have software 2.0. We could
look at the compressive or the semantic
distances like the model information
geometry looking at the statistical
different differences within some
trained information geometry space of
two inputs. That's kind of like vector
embeddings, cosine similarities and all
that. But what isn't out there yet? And
that's software 3.0. The numbers don't
really matter, but it's cognitive
computing distances. So, does that cup
of coffee taste the same to these two
people? Or do these two things appear
differently in light of this to that?
For a true perspectival cognitive
information theory, these are the
differences that make differences for
sophisticated cognitive agents. We need
to cover diverse and unknown
cognitive phenomena.
We're talking about systems that we
don't even know what they are as well as
the ones that we know well what they
are. We need to address disperate
systems from a first principles
perspective which is the high road and
that by specification includes systems
that we designed as well as built.
That's the low road. So it's like
there's the recipes that we can cook and
we should be able to describe those. But
then also we want that description
method to be able to describe recipes we
can't cook but we can dream up.
The active inference institute supports
reliable and effective applications of
cognitive computing and active inference
across domains
by providing key services such as
open-source software whether inference
libraries the ontology the generalized
notation notation cerebrum etc. the
repos that we host as well as the ones
that we just curate and give pathways to
like RX infert as well as education
mega exclamation point for that one
tech trees
professional training symposia
internships inerson educational programs
increasingly all these different things
and more to come
the metal rails of the physical supply
chain
have their own supply chain leading into
education and the mind of the engineer.
Just like dirt and asphalt roads, low
roads are built basically only where and
as needed, lest there be a bridge to
nowhere, which is wasteful at best, or
lest something natural and beautiful and
wild be covered up with a parking lot.
So even when we're talking about
physical roads,
they're not built everywhere. they're
built as useful. So when we're talking
about statistical probabilistic models,
we're talking about building what's
useful within a larger space of what
could be described.
Already there are many applications of
variational cybernetics which is to say
active inference by another name. So
whether you call it evidence lower bound
like elbow or whether you call it a free
energy functional or energy based model
if we're talking about systems that
include the sensory cognitive and output
actionoriented components and we're
fitting a variational bound it's active
inference and that's even considered
narrowly.
We have the curated implementations.
We have various agent models,
variational autoenccoders and far far
beyond. Especially if you take up that
triple equivalence.
If you take this triple equivalence
between neural networks, basing machines
seriously as Takuya isomer presents in
the guest stream 110.1
then the scope of the high road is
amazing in total. Consider
this cognitive research, education,
tech and infrastructure situation to be
analogous to the metallurgy and the
alchemy of high precision calipers which
can be used to describe or measure
machine parts during the material
industrial revolutions.
Hence our organizational focus on
accessibility, rigor, applicability
on education, sovereignty, supply chains
and security.
In this light and way, the active
inference
method tradition and the institute is at
the articulation
gap or blanket of syntax, semantics and
the specific and the general.
Think the center that holds the eye of
the storm, the strange attractor.
The information supply chain is the
spine or the railroad built on the rails
of GNN and other notation systems. And
the institute the pie is the golden
spike meeting at the middle of the high
road and the low road or coast to coast
AM which is just like the ephemeralized
version of the golden spike
and
showing here Alexandra's beautiful
ceramics.
We give her the last word on this
section.
Everything was halfbaked at some point.
All right.
I'm going to now look at the live chat.
So, I'm going to go to the horizontal
line. I will read these. So, if you have
any uh comments or questions,
write them in the chat and I'll get to
them. All right.
Alexander Hemming
writes, "Is there an option towards more
philosophical integration into the
research fellowship?" Yes. Yes, it could
be more philosophical or it could be
more technical. You could look at the uh
application page for some more
information, but sort of to use the
legacy system. It's kind of like
posttock level research that might be
done by a high schooler or somebody
who's far far outside of academia. So
it's not to say that you need a PhD at
all. There's no required degree, but
it's like you're proposing a program
that includes the possibility of
open-source dissemination, inclusion,
all these different kinds of aspects
that would make it relevant for being
hosted here. and it integrates with your
research inquiry at that kind of a big
level and opens up these channels and
provides email address affiliation etc.
And if it were philosophical in nature
wonderful
Andreas thank you for the comments.
Andreas writes, I'm seeking help to find
users who would be interested and also
modelers and developers in regards to
the grant that's being discussed.
And also consider and how to develop
this ecosystem and also consider what
other software like RX infer.jl and PMDP
and active inference.jl jail. What would
be good for our ecosystem?
Great. You know, ask not what the
ecosystem can do for you. Haptivist
writes,
"What is the basis of the collective
units, group, colony, etc.
Is there formal quantitatively described
definitions?
Yes. Descriptions? Yes.
So this is kind of like what the tech
tree looks like. It's like for a given
scale of analysis. Let's say we're
talking about online teams.
First, you know, awareness,
predescriptive awareness, then
metacognitive awareness, descriptive
awareness on through. So, do we have
executable simulations of multi-agent
online open science participatory
ecosystems? I don't. Maybe someone does.
But here's the tech tree. Here's the
path towards moving from
dreaming up what that party looks like,
what's being served at the party on
through the operational constraint
definitions of that recipe on through
dispatching that catering request to
your own kitchen or to another kitchen.
And then it's easy at the beginning to
say, well, I want there to be 500 people
and I want them to think that the soup
is awesome.
The soup being awesome is the assessment
at the end of that model. So yes, we
have some formal descriptions of nested
systems and part of the work is to move
those descriptions
and keep them all integrated
on through just the description like AOS
for agentic ontologies or just the
variational synthesis paper for re using
the reormalization group on through
being able to cash that check. cook that
recipe and use it in play and assess its
performance.
Pi 5549 writes, "Do you guys do regular
Discord open chats?" Yes, we have had uh
weekly open hours. So, if
uh the projects seem a little bit too
specific or you're not sure if some
topic or or mode of engagement is right
for uh project as listed, there is an
open hour, we're about to go on this
sort of break for July as we also will
in December. And when we come back,
there's no time set yet for the open
hour, but if someone just one person
raises their hand and says, "I will be
there Tuesdays at this time UTC." And
then if no one joins, no one finds out
and you get to hang out and study or do
whatever. Or maybe a bunch of people
join. So whoever wants to facilitate
that kind of an open session, just say
so. Could be whatever frequency,
whatever hour UTC, it's not awkward.
People are all over the world. People
have different sleepwake schedules,
different availabilities. So just put
out when you want it to be and say I
would go if it were at this time or I
will be the one to make it happen at
this time.
Active blueology. Hi
paradoxical AP3 says I know how to build
AGI. No cap.
sweating emoji. Okay, if you can put it
in the live chat, go for it. Otherwise,
thanks for sharing it.
All right, I'll wait just another minute
if anyone has any comments briefly just
for for screenshotting and our our
vision model colleagues. I'll just look
back through all the slides.
So, if you've gotten this far,
any of these links will take you where
you need to go. Blanket
atactiveinference.institute
is the inbox. You can send anything, any
question is there.
So
have some fun.
Uh I hope this has been a uh exciting
quarterly round table bringing the lab
meeting format to live streamed
genre and delivery.
uh look forward to a relaxing
July and to picking back up in the
second interval of activities where
we'll have the symposium, we'll have
other fun topics and projects. We're
going to have what people propose. And
during July, we will prune off the
projects that have gone inactive so that
the projects link always reflects what's
actually living.
and we will check in with the interns,
see who still is in the game. We will
open the doors. They're always open, but
point to them again for new interns,
people who want that structure, that
mentoring possibility, and uh hopefully
a few new research fellows.
A lot will be happening in the second
half of the year. So, I'll leave it on
Alexandra Ceramics to close.
Thank you everybody in the live chat.
See you next time.